I had an insight this morning down at
the barn shoveling poop so if you think
of culture as a grouping you know let's
say Christian culture Catholic
Catholicism as a culture or being an
American as a culture or certain
language you know I primarily defined
cultures language norms in taboo you
think of it as a grouping then the
people there's then that's what I would
you know think of as culture and when I
think of a collective I think of like if
you had all these little dots inside of
the culture and then in this grouping
had all these little dots the collective
was not something that was defined by
this context but was enacted in a
participatory manner so if this person
in this cultural grouping was talking to
this person was talking to this person
was talking to this person then in that
that time that duration to it during
which they were participating they were
actually something that wasn't bounded
but that was a morphic resonance and so
so was it was inherently cross-boundary
right so if you and I were in a
participatory discussion like we are now
and we were in from profoundly different
cultures then I would say that this is a
participatory field not a cultural field
so I started to think of the collective
as and I started to see some of the
confusion in some of the spiritual
traditions because the spiritual
traditions have always rejected culture
as an intermediary so most of the
spiritual traditions you do individual
practice and then that brings you to
that's the microcosmic level and that
gives you insight into the macrocosmic
cosmological and they've always rejected
the culture as being I mean the the
secular culture as being immediate me
Thierry the mistake that they make
though is than they made their religious
traditions or their lineages bound
identities and so what my insight was
the possibility that this new emergent
field a participatory collective that is
being enacted in real time was like the
miso cosmic order so you have the
microcosmic than the macrocosmic and
what was emerging was this miso cosmic
order and that solved another problem
another new conceptual nuisance that
I've had and that was this concept that
that when you move from the microcosmic
story of the individual enlightenment to
the macrocosmic story of cosmological
let's say evolutionary spirituality then
you can't derive a planetary ethos right
there's no there's there's no mezzo
structure in between and so with this
collective participatory collective you
could actually participate on a
planetary scale and so the story the
cosmological story story has to go
through like the geo history of the
planet the planet in the earth story
with the is the story that we shared the
cosmology so it kind of fit nicely into
this planetary ethos I had so just just
kind of making this distinction between
the collective as a participatory thing
and culture as it arises in our
evolutionary history as an exclusionary
principle was a little insight that I
had that I think I'm going
to use at least for a little while until
it becomes its own conceptual nuisance
huh oh my i really felt fit that felt
good and true yeah feels good it's got
some radical implications it means like
you know it says don't look for the
answers in statism or nation nationalism
or in the United Nations or in
interfaith dialogue right because all
those bounded cultures are there's some
confusion in what we've been waiting for
you know what we've been waiting for is
this other sense and this kind of fits
into your thing about theatre people
because it's a if you think of identity
of the collective as something that's
constantly enacted it's it's not it's a
fluid I forgot how you started off but
you said fluid something fluid
personalities or fluid roles or
flexibility in consciousness yeah so
it's cool because you'll see that the
morphic fields then at the human level
are constantly being enacted and arising
and emerging and having a vibrant kind
of network yeah that isn't that's that's
fluid and isn't just just niches and
boxes that people fit in and then there
has to be some kind of dialogue between
belief systems that for the most part in
commenced herbal so so it was an
interesting way of looking at things and
the other thing I like about it is that
the collective enactment doesn't can be
between human and human and human and
animal a human implant or human and
works of art you know you could have a
participatory experience with a work of
art and so it becomes very
a myriad display of something culture
true or false culture arises out of
participatory experience well we have to
know what we mean by culture and so in
my in my current understanding as it
composes itself I've been doing a lot of
studying on animism you know and
wondering you know where are we from
what what were humans born out of and
one of the things that I discovered was
because early animus mystic societies
not the one even societies it try little
you know tribes totemic totemic people
okay because the anthropologist went and
studied them and they found that totemic
people thought the buffalo were persons
and certain plants with persons and
certain rocks were persons they they
they misunderstood totemic people they
thought animism everything was
everything was imbued with
intersubjective qualities right well it
turns out this is a grave mistake that
that the early totemic cultures were
actually more exclusionary than us
because only some plants were persons
only some animals were persons and only
some humans were person oh and it gets
really really interesting so I guess is
this okay if this is one of the times I
talk a lot sure well we don't know what
we're doing yes okay so and this will
give you some insight into my insight so
this is what I've been learning I've
unlike third or fourth book and cultural
anthropology and animism and so what
what's very interesting so if you
imagine early man coming out of his
animal nature right in his
animal nature we have what i call
incompatible goods you know it's it's
good the Fox it's a rabbit so she can go
home and feed her bunnies but it's good
that the bunny goes home escapes and
goes home to feed her babies so so early
man is just part of this this natural
state of incompatible goods and then the
self consciousness into him is coming
and he understands that he can either
take the role of predator or prey and
what you see in these animistic society
says society is not a good word these
animals declans these doe tenant clans
is that they talk a lot about
shape-shifting so to be you're not
always a predator and you're not always
pray it depends upon the enactment and
so when the hunters go out to hunt they
get into this liminal space because they
don't know if they're humans because if
they get eaten they're not humans
they're dead already right and so you
get this this this sense that only some
people are humans and it's your clan and
your totems only some animals are sacred
because they're persons to so you would
never eat them and it's a constantly a
revolving door so if you're really
really sick your on your in the liminal
stager you may be dead already and
everything else is either a monster or
dead or not human including other people
and it's so exclusionary that if you
don't in that the the rules and rights
of the tribe you are then considered not
a person either right so you can be cast
out and you can't take care of yourself
so you would die so we start from
actually animism which is it
exclusionary more much more an
exclusionary principle as early man is
trying to understand their you know
starting to understand that there's this
role in between be
hangs out of this cut and a lot of that
what is established here are rules of
etiquette they're not etiquette like we
have them but they're around eating so
who gets to eat who who gets to be eaten
and we see this of course in
sophisticated rituals like Catholic
communion you know who gets to eat and
who gets to be eaten in taboos of all
sorts and so the religious impulse and
then then young fight late in his life
talked about the religious impulse being
this categorization of exclusions so
what is good versus what is bad what is
not you know all these normative rules
these negative dialectics and out of all
of that becomes culture right so it gets
more and more sophisticated the
categories get more sophisticated and so
the fundamental confusion about that
being a morphic field is that it has
that that it's basically an exclusionary
principle over time it's been expanded
and this is where you can be proud of
our modern society we actually include
more now you know so we're talking about
dolphins and we're talking about pets as
having rights so so this is this is kind
of interesting because the trajectory is
toward more inclusion of personhood and
to me that that's the collective that is
emergent and it's not coming through the
culture that that culture the great
waves of cultural arisings or emergence
or codifications have actually been
obstructions or obscure anchens or
something and this is resonates with
what spiritual traditions have often
said you know in or bundle really
struggled with it and it yeah I mean
it's a radical critique for example of
someone like Tejada shall dad who who
saw that culture and cultural learning
was the blossom on evolution and and and
so I would just switch the nuance
between culture as we know it and
collective as actually emergency
question here to open things up maybe is
so we have a cultural value now of
inclusion of including persons more and
more is that is a cultural principle of
inclusion the same as um you said what
was the word usage he's had a community
collective collective yeah yeah purchase
participatory collective pc right what
um well I uh I've been intuition on that
but I want to see where you go yeah so
so we're kind of making distinctions
that haven't been made before and
agreeing to say culture is something and
that is the exclusionary impulse and of
course all these these systems
self-maintaining self liberate right and
so as the process becomes more toward
participatory collective they become
trans cultural movements and they self
liberate so then i would say at a
certain point yeah so so in the
transitional phase is it is it the
language of culture of the language not
of culture and and I'm just trying to
make a distant want it to be a false
distinction I want it to be a new
distinction you know I don't I don't
want it to be imposed on what's real but
it perhaps can be a perspective that um
creates you know some my new years my
here's my sort of hit and understanding
yeah your word so far is that
participatory collective and / to end
participation
which is naturally inclusive nationally
inclusive happens in any culture between
cultures and and all and has happened
and can't happen in all times because
it's just about what happens between us
no matter who the US is or how many of
us there are when we get together and
racked and participate so it's not so
much about the the principles or Ted
booths or rules or understandings or
beliefs with which we operate amongst
ourselves or behave or exclude one
another so I was thinking even if even
if a cultural value becomes one of
inclusion a principle of inclusion it's
still operating a bit on a principle of
exclusion which is that our value is to
include as much as possible rather than
to exclude which either other people are
doing or we did in the past yeah the
operand operating on a principle in that
way is still not the same as what
happens when you simply when you just
when you engage with people and you part
it and you participate with them
everybody can participate well yeah yeah
what was slowed down so I would say and
so for the purposes of discussion i'm
going to be an advocate for my new idea
ok great so we can suss out whether it's
robust or something and instead of me
trying to beat up on myself with all my
own distinctions so I would say that not
everybody I would say from this new
position that um it was inconceivable
for early man to participate you just
couldn't I mean you couldn't go out and
when they you know especially if you
read these books it's kind of like the
river people ate pineapples they smell
the pineapples they were monsters so so
in the
clan it you just wouldn't you couldn't
get post formal as an early man and go
out and hang out with a river dweller it
turn it seems to me that the
exclusionary even the mind was excluded
from those kinds of ideas right so we're
talking about a radical shift here okay
and so yes they were just objects and
they couldn't be anything else yeah and
this one guy's trying to write about it
so he calls them sometimes monsters that
or sometimes they're just dead or their
objects or their monsters like
transitional forms but they're like
scary things you know they're not
they're not yeah you wouldn't
participate they have to be exercised
exercised or something so the fact that
you can make a statement like you just
did to me shows that the something
really novel has happened right so and
we know that there's ranges of that like
the status of personhood that slaves had
in different cultures sometimes they
were almost like people and they happen
to be caught up in a slave economy
sometimes they weren't really they
weren't people you know and so and then
we can think of the future where there's
a true participation with with what we
think has objects it's kind of
interesting you know and at scales that
are both what we consider self subhuman
like like a donkey or superhuman like
the planet or Gaia or something we don't
know this is that part is just truly
imaginary but then I think your your
statement about principles a
principle-based inclusion is still
exclusionary so this is not
principle-based because every time you
make a principle there's got to be
what's not what doesn't fit this is
participatory based and what's really
interesting is that it it it captures
something of a flavor of animism because
in animism even though it was
exclusionary
to be a person you had to enact
personhood you couldn't go and hang out
at the river and eat pineapples so it
takes that part it makes it less
principle and conceptual based when it
moves it into an inclusionary framework
without the meaning inclusion as being
principal day so that I think is that is
a good point that serves my argument why
I said thank you for making it yeah i am
here sir um i was i was thinking that
when you were talking about the future
of of a future where we can participate
with objects you know things that we
consider objects now I was thinking oh
yeah that's that's I mean that's obvious
like anything if I want to I can engage
with it as a thing over there that I is
basically a subtle dismissal or
disregard it's like a firm wall or
something but even even like the wall I
can turn to it and I can open in an
inner subjective way I can actually open
to it and see what it will teach me I
did this with like I was doing some
elemental meditations one day and I just
SAT by the water and I open to it and
you know dialogue you know but like
subtle to see what it what was for me
and taught me yeah and um yeah it seems
like there's actually limit to that but
it is a prize if you're saying it's not
it's an it's something that is a party
it's an enactment that's awesome because
because I I do this generative self
course right and then you go through
levels of shadow and shadow volt is
always that part that excludes right and
beneath the cultural level there's the
archetype in an animal level and then
there's elemental level and so I
actually never heard heard anyone say
that they did it elemental contemplation
or elemental meditation but but I know
the Zen Buddhists do this you know they
I mean the traditional very archaic old
tradition of they meditate in front of
rotting corpses so they can be quantum
asst between form and life and death
form and formlessness elementals all the
way down and and these are very very
profound what I call you know deep
phenomenology shadow practice so that's
really cool because because that and of
course opening up to something that's an
object is got that feeling of being
participating somehow you know and one
of the one of the things that I find
helpful but it's it's certainly not
necessary is instead of calling it into
subjectivity instead of using what's the
subject and what's object we work with
this notion of agency okay so if i look
at the wall it has a lot of agency i
mean i know it has a lot of agency
because if i run into it isn't going to
move you know I mean agencies is that
kind of solidity is it is an agency you
know and the other thing I like the way
I like to talk about agency is like the
great migrations and the sarin when the
Serengeti plains flood Neil that great
wildebeest and elephant and hippopotamus
migrations right so we see the animals
of it having agency but you can you can
actually see that the water has so much
agency the hue that it draws enormous
numbers of animals so once you start
playing with and and so for me this is
neo animism and that is not that things
you know not only is concept of making
persons but to see that everything has
agency and and sometimes the things that
we think has the least agency like you
know physical objects in the universe
like weather actually have the most
agency and and and that discussion is
really fastening and then it becomes
truly participatory hmm well I know I
it's still confusing to me whether the
the wall the wall is a good example cuz
it feels dead it's not like the water
like elements actually feel alive in
some way but the wall feels dead and
we're never alive something like that
and it's not clear to me that it has its
own subjectivity or something yes I
don't know where the communication or
the relationship or the teaching us from
and I don't know if it's receiving
anything from me but I can still I can
still participate in the same way I
participate with you I can still do the
same energetic I like the word an
enactment yeah I can take I can enter
the same energetic stance temporarily
that I would with anyone if I want to be
more present with them and open to them
more fully I can do that with anything I
don't know what it does to that thing
yeah you know what it does to me well
you know I think the wall Wilbur would
say it's a it's a heap it's not a whole
lot so you know we can I'm and these are
just techniques to describe our
relationship so you could say you know I
don't have relationship with the wall
but but I know that my cells are
exchanging electrons and photons with
the atoms in the wall but I would argue
that the wall has has agency in the
sense that it's in relation to its in
structural relationship to gravity for
example which is why it stands as a wall
and so actually gravity has agency so
you know these are just these are just
they're not important distinctions
they're just different ways of how you
can describe the experience of
participation with something like a wall
or
if it if it was a wall like you know the
Vietnam Memorial it would have a
different sort of participation and how
you talk about that is just yeah it
feels like there's a lot of tension
there what it feels exciting in the same
way that a lot of the inner subjective
practice groups feel exciting I like
pointing out that we can consciously
participate together and and see what
happens like a new like a new tool a new
organ to develop much more fully than we
have as yet so let's come back to what
you were talking about with
participatory cut it yeah is there more
is it our direction that we were going
because I have another question but no
I'm pretty much wrapped up with that so
all right so so let's let's let's keep
going there because I like participatory
collective it feels more exciting to me
then cold then culture feels beautiful
enjoyable full of value as we are
talking about it like to exclude things
is to create oneself so there's lots of
beauty that gets created lots of insight
that one has by excluding other things
but participatory collectives as we're
talking about them feel like they have
more potential to sort of meet us in our
personhood and also treat to treat
ourselves as persons even more fully and
also to help us go where we all want to
go as as people on the planet um so I'm
wondering now and I think distinction
between principles of inclusion still
being culture and participatory
collective still being something else
than that I think that worthwhile for
now so now I'm wondering what happens if
we keep engaging in participatory
collectives does culture come out of
that does it never come out of that or
you know I have lots of friends who are
in two different things different you
know kind of like leading edge things
and it feels like lots of people are
trying to create a new culture trying to
create a like a Western or American
culture or something that has some depth
some depth to it and so you know what so
there's just a question of what the
relationship is between these two things
I mean in a way especially in when in
the collective participation groups that
you know I'm thinking of the spiritual
groups for example there's a lot of
emphasis on what's new and what's
unknown what's coming next and when I
engage in that sort of relationship to
the present moment and into my
interactions with people it actually
doesn't feel like like there's much that
gets deeply established or rooted in the
way that like culture or history feels
like it's deeply established and rooted
because it feels more like like Terry
cotton weave saying it's like a practice
and so what gets established is a praxis
but what's happening between us is novel
and I don't know if that what that leads
to in terms if you do it long term with
a group of people you know repeatedly
whatever that creates culture yeah I
mean I'm arguing that culture originally
comes out of this exclusionary has this
exclusionary aspect to it and is
maintained by ritualized participation
right that that that there's don't
really want to use participatory
collective because it's
such a modern way to think of first you
have to be an individual to think of
participatory collective and that early
man was less individuated at all that he
that's even ma you know another modern
phase but I think part of this is kind
of like what we're talking about
personality I mean your uniqueness is
going to come up and you're going to
have a default pattern especially if
you're not experimental about yourself
or not a theater person and that's okay
as long as we don't ratify it you know
so you take a snapshot of it I mean this
is of course one of one of the things we
do all the time you know you have a nice
thanksgiving and then you want to do it
the same way next year and you do it the
same way next year and it was nice but
then at a certain point the fact that
it's always the same actually becomes a
burden and and and so there's there's
that mixture of when is something kind
of falsely rarified and when is
something just kind of and re-enacted in
a participatory way and I think that's
true for the ego and the personality you
know to have a stable way if that you
show up in the world is not a bad thing
but if it's falsely rarefied so so
you're actually putting an effort to
show up that way when it's a disconnect
with what you actually feel or something
then then there's a problem so i would
say in many aspects today a lot of what
is culture is falsely rarefied and
intercourse it's all you know we see
that that's where people actually
working on their cultures right so
fundamentalism is the opposite move
fundamentalism is the move to go back
and more strongly reify the symbols and
systems that are not actually
enacted in a participatory way a young
child you know a young child in the
modern world on the internet who is so
you know being forced to marry an 80
year old cousin is probably not enacting
the culture in a participatory way so
leads can lead to false false
consciousness even though there could be
a lot of group cohesion but it's it's
it's not you know things a lot of the
individual need a lot of things have
changed so now it's a false
consciousness
ok here's another distinction to make um
culture as um as as behavior and rules
that come from exclusionary yeah
exclusions I'm different kind I suppose
yeah excuse me our principles um the
praxis of opening in participation with
someone or something and then that gets
mixed of what a thing or a person is and
then but what about just what happens
between two energy fields like weather
eye open to you or not we're interacting
I don't have to do a practice for us to
be participating together I don't have
to do a practice to be affected by the
walls and the floor and that seems like
even more inclusive because it's just
instant innate it's just the fact of
being affected by one another yeah so
now we have to you know at a certain
level everything is always participating
with everything else there's no there's
no exclusion and that realization makes
participatory collective participation
easy because everything's just always so
so you know I could play the devil's
advocate I don't really believe this but
you know since we're playing around with
these definitions I could play the
devil's advocate and say that's
precisely why all cultures are merely
exclusionary efforts because you take
away the exclusionary effort and all you
have is participation so I could say
that what we're always doing is calling
from the sum total or participation
transformational identities which is
cool as long as you don't verify them so
from that perspective
could actually make a stronger argument
against these summits of identity I like
it because I actually like adding that
the third tier because it it instead of
making it polar what we're talking about
it makes it more of a spectrum yeah
because even the even in that middle way
of the Praxis of being participatory
with someone else like you're talking
about Thanksgiving dinner or something
like that we have to pick up we have to
use every behavior is a canary it's this
behavior not that behavior when you bite
people you don't invite other people
right so like we have to use culture
while we're being open to one another
yeah and you separated you know they
can't be totally separated yeah and the
key is the way we see it today is to
have that be a viable fluid um semi
permeable membrane not a bounded prison
you know not not like if you go down the
river and eat pineapples you're not a
human you know so that's a little friend
for all times you know except it doesn't
last for all times because these these
structures self liberate and that's not
because its peak seems to be a universal
law or something but yeah so in that
sense it's a both and I don't want to
make a universal principle out of my
insight I just it's to me an insight the
purpose of an insight is nothing to
clutch onto as universal waiting for
another insight is to is to make what
was either nuisance or some kind of
solid thing more alive has more life in
it you know I like it the purpose of
insight is to make something that was
solid have more aliveness in it yeah I
like it too yeah and I think what
happens is this is why some of these
spiritual technologies are both
fantastic and problematic because they
do that they make something that was
solid have more life and then people
make that into a solid thing you know
and this is this is the move that is
that is counter punctual to actual
insight you know Rick said some
important things today already so I
think we've said important things and
let me let me we could forget them okay
whistles older don't forget that the
only thing that's gonna remember
everything is the Akashic record you
know that's the only thing that's gonna
remember everything we're always
forgetting well and the organism somehow
always remember is still fun Oh
interesting I think um okay let's see
don't quiet see anything wants to
participate Oh we'll have to make
exclusions okay I want to go further
okay okay this leads in important
directions that I often go okay two
things one
there's a bullet head if there's like a
bullet which I don't think it's really
bulleted that's to drop no that's okay
yeah just that's fine continue we're
like a landscaper exploring here um okay
here's one thing when everything becomes
um we've talked about this before but
the movement we just made and the
pointing out of what insight is for is
something that I end up coming back to a
lot I think and it has to do with the
the when everything everything from the
deepest you know fundamental insights to
the most concrete personal requirements
becomes relation alized and so
everything is relation alized there
seems with the next step always seems to
me is deep pragmatism like what is
anything for in relationship to
everything else and is that where I want
to go and I see that deep pragmatism
opening up in spirituality more and more
I see it opening up in relationship to
culture more and more in relationship to
disciplines in relationship to education
health there's like this deep question
we have access to lots of stuff what are
they for where do we want to go and then
end of refocusing on value values so
that's one one direction or another
direction is that somehow the
somehow saying somehow that pragmatism
often comes to me with a feeling of
tragedy like everything gets relation
alized and then so it loses its own it
loses its independence it loses its
independent meaning and even purpose
like where we want to go together is
relation alized in this in this space so
it too is only it's like I'm shading
towards knee ilysm I can feel it but I
don't quite know how to get out of it
but just like today and yesterday that
tragedy is sort of like switched into
humor why I started laughing because
everything is it's just it's just funny
it's just like there's no you can't
can't land anywhere and it's just funny
it's rigged I still feel regret it I
still feel like it's regrettable that
everything becomes utilitarian eyes Dan
and becomes pragmatic in this way it
again there's still there's these shades
of need ilysm in there um but I recycle
through this what we've just done here I
recycle through this a lot i'm wondering
what comes next and where yeah what
comes next basically um
yes so so i think that the situation
obviously becomes more exasperated the
more significant the insight right so if
you have a significant insight into the
nature of reality or the emptiness of
self something like that and it
overwhelms right it overwhelms and then
there can be what I would call and I'm
not saying this is what you said because
I'll just start talking and then maybe
in some where here is what you said or
more more idea of what we're saying okay
I'm not saying this is what you said but
so you have these significant insights
and then there can be this experience of
frameshift so either I'm in this
significant insight frame or I'm in this
ordinary frame and they don't seem to
really have that it's not necessarily
their intention they're just in this too
much of an either/or kind of situation
that feels comfortable so I either
relativize the significant insight add
something practical or I'm in a state of
nihilism and say everything that's
practical is so relativized by the
significant insight it doesn't may have
any meaning anymore so that's something
that you know I've experienced is the
sense that there's just frameshifting
rather than it's like you need an
insight on these these two things now
you know and then that of course can
come with the same problem so that that
I can see would tend and then it could
be funny because what's funny is that
that they're like jokes of each other
it's like it's like that thing I always
say how much does the scale way you know
that question is is a relational joke so
so I don't know how to answer that
question but what came up for me was
this concept of this notion of effort
you know this is a very richly nuanced
word in taoism effortless effort and I
think that that the nihilism comes into
play when you think you have to add
effort to make the insight practical and
and I don't even know how to game up in
me but that's the that it's like
it changes your world it changes your
behavior and that alone is somehow
pragmatic even though we wouldn't
necessarily know so it's not
instrumentalized we didn't put it in
intrumental package but it's it's shaped
something and that so to me that that's
a pragmatic thing even though we don't
necessarily know how to name it or
create meaning from it so the ordination
it's not like the ordinary ships but the
ordinary is now headed in a different
direction than it would have otherwise
been even though it just feels just as
ordinary and relative as it did before
so that would be a little story that I
would tell and it's not really an
explanation because it doesn't really
fit but yeah but but my sense of that
that that places this concept of
framesets which without really yeah
mm-hmm mm-hmm I mean in a way there's a
parallel
I have to say don't have the problem
anymore so it's some well that's great
yeah my anguish is that it's not it's a
non necessary problem but I can't cite
and I haven't moved through it yet you
know I have not moved through it yet um
but it feels like there's a parallel
need to do a caveat here because my
understanding spiral dynamics is
actually not that deep but it feels like
there's a parallel to the shift from
like green to yellow well if green is
like things are relative eyes yeah Liz
like okay but what do you care about
like what's most work like there's still
better things than other things you know
yeah this pragmatism yeah I think that
that's that's a good description of the
cognitive tension between those two
operational levels the difficulty is in
the reason why it's good that you're in
is too many people because green and
relativism is so hard too many people
would kind of discard it to get to this
faux yellow right if we're going to talk
in these terms so that so that things
become simpler but because but they
become simple in a reduced way if you
truly commit to the skill sets and
capacities at the pluralistic stage that
shift is much harder because it's not
that the relativistic view goes away
it's that and something else you know
this is why the term transcend and
include is difficult because when people
think of transcending pluralistic
there's a sense that oh done with all
that difficulty now pluralism is always
difficult right it's always difficult so
so that so the fact that you're still
there and it's more complex is to me a
sign that it's healthier and I think
that you
have intuitively identified people that
have made the move in this false way I
mean you can just tell I mean they've
got something of the integrative aspect
but they no longer include the
pluralistic that the immensely complex
situation of the pluralistic viewpoint
is too easy to skip through it's very
very yeah I think it's very it's a very
big skill sets challenge and to say that
this isn't that the way I'm describing
it isn't isn't only and not even
primarily cognitive the way I wrote it
is like very much so fusing everything
could say it's this Robles not only
visceral either it's like everything all
everything and so it goes really deep
good yeah yeah it's a whole paradigm you
know it's it's it's the way values come
up it's the way you just described
spiritual insight gets relativized
everything is always i wanna i wanna
touch it on this relativize word so I
owe you called it now here's interesting
million ask you this question you use
the word I wrote it down relation alized
versus relativize yes yeah I did that on
purpose yeah so let's talk about that I
wrote it down cuz I think there's a
couple things here which i haven't
actually teased out fully so this will
be novel for me okay so here's the story
I so my main feature is Samuel blonder
and waiting down crew and sandals guru
would whom he lived with closely for 18
years maybe 20 or something like that 18
years i think was um adi da and at some
point in a das own
practice life a major inquiry for him
major major inquiry was avoiding
relationship ? a Mayan voiding
relationship and that somehow has seeded
is has been a seed for my for my own my
own insights into what this world is and
it's made out of and relationship feels
like the best word for it like not
emptiness or it's not being is not one
taste I mean all of those things are
true too but if you get down to the
paradox of self and other like at all
scales what feels like is going on at
all moments is relationship and that
somehow seems to contain the impersonal
and the personal at the same time
everything is relationship so that feels
warm to me and it feels profound where
the world where the word relativized has
connotations of flattened or less and
less significant or something like that
and that's not that's not what I mean
nice I mean although like I said there's
some shades of that which come with this
feeling of me ilysm but but it's
actually more like intimacy like
engaging intimately everything is
engaging intimately at all times with
with each with each other and that
intimacy feels like the heart of what's
going on here yeah I mean I I would say
that my use of the term relativized
should be interpreted more like describe
the leash
can relation alized relativism actually
comes from you know fixing a frame of
reference or value and the point is
those fixed frames are relative because
everything is relation alized right so
relation alized is the reason why we
come up with this apparent illusion of
relative values and relative this and
relative that so yeah that's it that's a
good distinction I think and thinking of
you know of course it's interesting
because we think of these as cultural or
interpersonal interest objective
paradigm shifts but science also often
leads in in the interpretation of
reality it when you know there is in a
lot of quantum science now they talk
about there are no things there's only
events and events are only relations you
know there's just relational fields and
and then people like to lose and
Guittard and there they you know there's
a lot of people who have moved toward
this kind of new event relations
cosmology languaging what it what things
what things what are not things but just
just as you said so instead of saying
for example the pen n theists were hard
strong to say there's consciousness all
the way up and all the way down that
that gets a little tricky but if you say
there's relationship all the way and up
and down within the relationship between
a purse a human and a human is not only
different than the relationship and Adam
and an atom has but it's still
relationship there's different ranges
a relationship that humans and humans
can have right so so that word kind of
serves serves better than than some of
the other ways of describing it so how
does Neil ism why would this view of a
relation alized reality play with this
this notion of neil ism how do i how
what's the relationship between that you
know yeah I mean so so we said when you
to use the term relative we understand
how that sits with neo lozeau more is
more prone to knee ilysm so let's let's
move the concept of knee ilysm into this
notion of relation alized right
for myself I don't know um it could be
that I like what you said about putting
in too much effort to make an insight
practical like that feels like a very
very strong potential and or wanting to
like holding on to a certain ideas of
showing up in the world in certain ways
or wanting to be successful which I
still want but in ways that are maybe
somehow creating like more feelings of
darkness and tragedy or something like
that no it's it's unclear yeah I'm like
sitting I'm just like total I'm in the
middle of it and it's and it's not clear
another thread for me is again somehow
this the relational izing of and
everything even life and death makes it
both feel like it's a possibility that I
can't escape the world even even if I
were to die anyway yet at the same time
life itself and engagements with life
are all sort of yeah it's very personal
it's very personal you know and
sometimes they're losing their
excitement or their flavor and I'll but
there is something to effort you know
like at least for where I'm at now the
lesson that I'm learning is not has not
been effortlessness the lesson that I've
learning is that all things that are
worthwhile take continued effort and
work to bring to fruition mm-hmm that's
a burden you know that's i'm not
actually all that good at at practice
yeah so there's that's a
you know there's something there too for
me the the personal problem I said this
the other day I when I said in a joke
book you know we're talking about I was
talking to somebody who's basically a
business person and wanted to skype with
me and wanted to learn from me and as as
quite often happens the business person
has done a lot of things in their lives
been quite successful has a brand does
consulting blah blah blah but they end
up being bored right so we were talking
around a little bit he wanted to learn
for me and then he says well frankly you
know I'm kind of bored and so I was
talking of telling the story to a friend
of mine and I was saying well I'm never
bored but but I'm probably irrelevant
right so here's the deal there's the
other side of it you know and so this
person is in real name and has real
money and goes all over the world and
can feel relevant in in their world of
boredom and I'm never bored but I
actually feel pretty irrelevant to that
to that world and so we had a good laugh
about that and that's what I mean about
not the effort in doing the work I
certainly put in a lot of effort to do
all the things that I do that are
relevant but I can't really put any
effort into making myself relevant
because it's not it's not it's not
within my control you know it's just and
it's the same thing whether it's
practical I think practical is a curious
too practical relative to being relevant
to what you know so we had a good laugh
at that
so I yeah so my my word for my worry is
that that I'm completely irrelevant yeah
like I put all this work and I think I
have all these good ideas and you know I
think rather fondly of my productivity
and then at the end of the day it seems
quite irrelevant so just a different
take on it I guess well but I'm not
bored right I know I would hope that in
time you feel more relevant that you are
seen as relevant um the other thing
that's interesting here is that I have
heard that people who are successful
there's a story there is a story and I
actually don't know how true it is i
miss me I'm yes a myth there's a myth
there's a myth that people on their
deathbed who have had very effective or
very um big lives or something look back
and they think what was that all four I
wish I had spent more time with my
family what's good like that and at
least you're living in your irrelevance
consciously now yeah and just on your
death you know there's this great line
in this kind of horse guru I have and he
has a video and he says of course he's
you know his charisma is just
outstanding and he says I promise you
it'll the little things that you will
remember when it comes to the day you're
going to die the leave here's an accent
danish accent the leave they leave on
the river the touch of your lover's hand
that's what you'll remember I promise
you he says so that's the same thing you
know just just
trusting it gets it gets transmitted
from so many different wise people that
we have to trust it you know and and i
do i yeah
I used to be bored when I was a child do
it was awful I you know I can remember
being and I can remember that feeling of
having energy and being bored you know
with it that's that's a it's an
interesting state
and I guess that's one of those little
things you'll remember because I can
remember my mom thing as mothers are you
know you when you're bored like that and
you're a kid you torture your mom you
know and then she says oh do you want
something to eat and it's and then she
goes to the cabinets do you want this do
you want that no do you want this no you
know we're just trying to be in service
but basically you're bored and you just
want to attack someone or make trouble
or something because if you if you get a
fight with your sister than at least
you're not bored you know in this
feeling of that energy I wonder how many
wars have been started because people
are deeply born I'm telling you it's an
interesting yeah talk about agency yeah
so um yeah okay maybe that's uh maybe we
could stop there we've been going for a
while yeah and so yeah I think we
covered some grounds it has supreme
irrelevant see oh I love it well not
really it sounds like the title of the
modern American Tibetan Tantra know if
you like my gravestone I was supremely
irrelevant